Africana Studies, Department of; Records ua611
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Department of African American Studies Records
1968-1976
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua611
2.33 cubic ft. processed to date
The Department of African American studies documents the papers and administrative processes of the development and implementation of an African American Studies department at the University at Albany in the late 1960s to the late 1970s.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Web Archives
Access
Access to these records is unrestricted except where otherwise noted in the finding aid
Acquisition Information
These records were transferred to the University at Albany, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections, by the chairs of the Department of African and Afro-American Studies.
Administrative History
The current department of Africana Studies is the successor to the Department of Afro-American Studies created in January 1969. The department was part of the Division of Social and Behavioral Sciences of the College of Arts and Science, which became the College of Social and Behavioral Sciences in 1977. The Afro-American Studies department was created by President Collins in response to demands by an increasing African American student population, lead by the Black Student Alliance, for entry level courses in Afro-American studies. On January 31, 1969, President Collins by-passed normal University channels and formed an Afro-American Studies Department scheduled to offer courses in the fall of 1969.[1] Previous to the formation of the Africana Studies Department courses had been offered during the 1960's in the departments of English (Afro American Literature Eng 583 was introduced in the Fall of 1966), History (History of the Negro in the United States, HY 254 was introduced in the fall of 1966), Sociology (Minority Groups, Soc 150, introduced in Fall of 1964). These courses would eventually form the basis for the interdisciplinary Afro-American Studies Department.
According to the 1969-1970 bulletin of the new department, "The Department of Afro-American Studies was designed...[to] supplement...the intellectual perspectives which have been characteristic of our nations historically pro-white orientation. This would be accomplished through an investigation of vital disciplines such as political, historical, economic, socio-psychological and derived issues as they relate to the Black experience."[2] According to the University Final Budget request for 1970-71 the new department would concentrate specifically on "Urban Affairs and human development."[3] Though the primary focus of the department was studying the black experience in the United States, from the start the department also included courses relating to African history and culture.
The new department developed rapidly. The 1970 University Bulletin lists thirty-four courses available to an undergraduate major in Afro-American Studies in the areas of Historical Issues, Economic-Political, Socio-Psychological, or Cultural.[4] Since the Fall of 1972 the department has offered a Masters of Arts degree.[5]
In addition to its strictly academic course offerings, the African and Afro-American Studies Department served as a social support arena. It was and is the only department in which there is a substantial number of black professors, providing students with needed role models in a predominately white environment. The department serves as a home for mentors and those to be mentored.
In 1973 the Department Afro-American Studies enlarged their mission to give equal emphasis to the interdisciplinary study of Africa. In recognition of this new emphasis the Afro-American Department changed its name to the Department of African and Afro-American Studies. In 1990 the department once again changed its name to Africana Studies in recognition of a new widening of its intellectual focus--namely the inclusion of courses documenting the whole African diaspora. New areas of concentration included Caribbean and Latin American Studies.
Notes
[1] Draft letter of President Evan R. Collins to Faculties ,Senate,Ca. January 20,1969; Official Listing of Black Students AllianceDemands, January 13, 1969.
[2] The State University At Albany, Undergraduate Bulletin, 1970-71, p. 152.
[3] State University of New York at Albany, Final Budget Request, 1970-71, p. 51.
[4] State University of New York at Albany, Undergraduate Bulletin, 1970-71, p. 152-55.
[5] State University of New York at Albany, Graduate Bulletin 1972-73, p. 61
Scope and Contents
Contains the chair's correspondence of the Departmentof Afro-American (1969-1973) and subsequently African and Afro-American Studies(1973-1976) regarding the formation of the department in 1969 and it's subsequentdevelopment, as well as correspondence with colleagues in the professioninterested in the process by which the department was founded, and relatingto the formation of the Council on Afro-American Studies in 1969-1970.Also contained in the records are department faculty minutes (1969-1973),proposals Afro-American Studies Department, a "The Minority Summer Institute"(1971); requests for assistance in the development of a Puerto Rican Studiesdepartment; and a few faculty publications.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Ethnic Groups; Africana Studies; African-American studies; Higher education and society; Afro-American Studies; Higher education and state--United States.; Albany (N.Y.); Newsletters; Administrative records; Membership; Minutes; Programs (documents); Financial Records; Web Archives; UAlbany Academic Departments; The Department of African American Studies
- Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976, Undated; 1; 1.33 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Afro-American Studies Department and Program, 1970-1971 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1973 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 2)
  - Annual Report, 1975-1976 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 3)
  - Assignments and Syllabi, 1973 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 4)
  - Black Educators Conference Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 5)
  - Black Faculty and Staff Organization, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 6)
  - Bibliography of Faculty, 1973 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 7)
  - Budget Documents and Correspondence, 1970 April-1972 March (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 8)
  - Budget Documents and Correspondence, 1972 April-1973 March (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 9)
  - Buffkins, Dr. Archie, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 10)
  - Bulletin, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, Misc., 1968-1979 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 14)
  - Correspondence on Workshops, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 15)
  - Correspondence Received, 1971-1972 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 16)
  - Correspondence Received, 1974 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 17)
  - Correspondence on Research, 1974 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 18)
  - Correspondence Sent, 1969 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 19)
  - Departmental Beginnings, 1968-1970 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 20)
  - Departmental Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 21)
  - Departmental Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 22)
  - Departmental Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 23)
  - Enrollment Data, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 24)
  - Faculty Committee Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 25)
  - Faculty Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 26)
  - Faculty Meeting, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 27)
  - Faculty Meeting, 1970-1971 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 28)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1972 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 29)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 30)
  - Faculty Staffing, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 31)
  - Faculty Staffing, 1972-1973 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 32)
  - Graduate Committee, 1971-1973 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 33)
  - Graduate Assistants Correspondence & Memorandums, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 34)
  - Graduate Information, 1972-1973 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 35)
  - Graduate Students Handbook, undated (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 36)
  - Guest Lecturer Annoucements, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 37)
  - Hampton Associates, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 38)
  - Harris,Fred, 1970 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 39)
  - The Holt Collection, 1969 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 40)
  - Honorarium Request Forms, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 41)
  - Ibadan University - Nigeria, applications for, 1972-1973 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 42)
  - Independent Undergrad Study Proposals, 1972-1973 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 43)
  - Interfuture Program, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 44)
  - Jackson, Dr. Jacquelyne, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 45)
  - Master of Art Degree Program Purpose, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 46)
  - Masters Program Proposal/Related Correspondence, Folder 1, 1969-1971 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 47)
  - Masters Program Proposal/Related Correspondence, Folder 2, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 48)
  - Memorandums, 1972 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 49)
  - Memorandums, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 50)
  - Minority Graduate Recruitment, 1971-1973 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 51)
  - Minutes, Faculty Meeting, 1972 (Box 1 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 52)
  - Miscellaneous, 1970 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1972-1974 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 2)
  - New York State Conference, 1976 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 3)
  - Obradovic, Dr., 1970-1971 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 4)
  - Okonko Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 5)
  - Programs/Announcements, 1976-1985 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 6)
  - Proposal to Nigerian Trip, 1973 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 7)
  - Prospects for World Peace, 1973 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 8)
  - Puerto Rican Studies Course Proposal, 1970 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 9)
  - Research Project, 1971 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 10)
  - Registration Information, 1973 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 11)
  - Schedule of Classes, 1972; 1974 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 12)
  - Staff Publications, 1974 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 13)
  - Stokes, Dr. Olivia Pearl, 1969-1970 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 14)
  - Student Papers, 1970 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 15)
  - Suggested Fall Courses, 1973-1974 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 16)
  - Thornton, Virginius B., 1969-1971 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 17)
  - Three Year Plan, 1976 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 18)
  - Undergraduate and Graduate Studies Foldout, Undated (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 19)
  - Wesley, Dr. Charles H., 1969 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 20)
  - Wheeler, Paul, 1970-1971 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 21)
  - YWCA of Albany Black History Month Essay Contest, 1987 (Box 2 (1-Chair's Subject Files, 1969-1976), Folder 22)
- Web Archives, 1999 January 27-2016 September 18; 2; 812 captures
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Web crawling is managed through the Internet Archive's Archive-It service. This page includes links to both the university's collection and the Internet Archive's public collection.
  Surface-level crawling of www.albany.edu is performed daily which should includes most top-level webpages. Separate targeted crawls of every albany.edu subdomain are performed monthly to attempt to gather all content. This includes: www.albany.edu, www.rna.albany.edu, www.ctg.albany.edu, www.ualbanysports.com, www.albany.edu/rockefeller, www.albany.edu/cela, www.albany.edu/asrc, m.albany.edu, library.albany.edu, events.albany.edu, cstar.cestm.albany.edu, csda.albany.edu, and alumni.albany.edu
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Web Archives
  - http://www.albany.edu/africana/ - University Archives collection, 2013 May 8-2016 September 18 (Web-archive 1)
  - WARC file for http://www.albany.edu/africana/, (please see https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_ARChive for more details), 2013 May 8-2016 September 18 (Warc 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    WARC files are very large and difficult to work with. Your request may take time to process, and we may be unable to deliver your request remotely. Please consult an archivist if you are interested in researching with web archives.
  - http://www.albany.edu/africana/ - Internet Archive collection, 1999 January 27-2016 September 18 (Web-archive 2)